Hey everyone, welcome back to the channel.
I hope you guys are doing extremely well.
So this video is going to be another video from the Strivers A to Z DSA course.
And this is India's most in-depth DSA Algo course.
Why do I see that?
Because this course has 455 modules.
I can guarantee you that you can take any paid batches, any free courses, none of those
courses will have 455 modules.
This is an extremely in-depth DSA Algo course that can teach you everything in-breath about
DSA Algo.
And in the previous videos, we have covered step 1.1 and 1.2.
And regarding step 1.3, I've added a video on C++ STL on the playlist.
You can go and watch it.
Regarding Java collection, I'll be adding a video in the future, not now.
If you need a video now, you can go to YouTube and you'll find a lot of other resources from
where you can study.
So in this video, we will be discussing about basic maths.
Why am I teaching just the basic maths as of now?
So you're starting off as of now, your brain will not be that mature.
So if I teach you the advanced level concepts, you might understand, but it won't be that
convenient for you.
That is why my teaching way is very different.
What I do is I usually start off with the basic stuffs.
I give you a lot of time to absorb it and then we move on to the advanced part.
This is why all the basic stuffs are initially there.
And then we move on to the DS Algo and in the step 8, we have a section as advanced
mathematics.
I'll be covering everything that is related to advanced mathematics that might be asked
in interviews.
But as of now, we will be learning basic maths.
Now these are the problems which we will be solving.
But before that, let's learn some basic maths concept.
So before solving all the problems that are listed under basic maths, we'll be starting
off with the basic maths concept.
I'll be teaching you the concepts initially and then we can solve all the problems listed
under the section.
The first concept that I'll be teaching you is the digit concept.
Remember one thing, this is a very, very important concept because if you know how to play around
digits, then you'll be able to solve most of the problems in basic maths.
Let's understand the digit concept.
Imagine I give you a number like 7789.
This is the number that I'm giving you.
Now I ask you to perform extraction of digits.
I ask you to perform extraction of digits.
Let's learn the extraction of digits and after that you will see how we can implement the
extraction of digits in order to solve most of the problems.
So when I say extraction of digits, what does it mean?
It means I need 9, I need 8, I need 7, I need 7, I need all the digits individually.
So what is this digit?
9.
Can I say this?
If I do a module of 10, I'll actually get 9.
Now you might ask, why?
If I ask you the numbers that are divisible by 10, what are they?
10, 20, 30, 40, 50, 60, 70, so on, 100 and so on, do you see a pattern?
All the numbers that are divisible by 10 are actually ending with 0, is it?
Right?
So can I say, if I'm doing a module of 10, what is the meaning of module operator in
basic maths?
The module operator says, I will divide the number by 10 and whatever is the remainder,
that is what I'll give you.
So if I see, if I'm dividing this number by 10, what is the nearest number?
Obviously, that will be 7, 7, 8, 0.
If I divide it by 10, this is what the nearest number will be.
And can I say that the remainder then will be 9?
Because if I divide it by 10, then this is where the division, like this is the number
which will get divided by 10.
And after that, we'll be left out with 9.
That is why when you do a module of 10, you always get the last digit, you get the last
digit as 9.
So this is how you get the 9 digit.
If I ask you, can I get the next digit 8?
How will you get the next digit 8?
Very simple.
You say, okay, this number, let's divide it by 10.
So if I divide 7, 7, 8, 9 by 10, can I say I'll get 7, 7, 8, 0.9?
Can I say this?
If I divide the number 7, 7, 8, 9 by 10, I'll get 7, 7, 8, 0.9.
And if I take an integer round off, if I take an integer portion of it, the integer portion
is 7, 7, 8.
So what you will do is, in order to go to the next step, you will say, divide by 10.
If you do a division by 10, you'll actually get 7, 7, 8, 0.9, but you just take the integer
part.
That is why you get 7, 7, 8.
So once you have 7, 7, 8 with you, if I need the last digit, which is 8, how do you extract
it?
Again, the same way, you say, can I divide, modularize with 10?
If I do a mod of 10, I'll actually get 8, why?
Because the nearest number will be 7, 7, 0, which is divisible by 10, which will still
leave a remainder of 8, so I get the digit 8 as well.
Now, can I see if I require the next digit 7, can I again do a division by 10?
If I do a division by 10, can I say I'll get 77, why?
Because if I write 7, 7, 8 by 10, I'll get 77.8, and the integer portion is 77, so I
get 77.
Again, if I have to extract the last digit, can I say I'll do a modularize, a modular
of 10, and I'll get 7?
Again, I will, hence I've again extracted 7, now if I need the next extraction, I again
divide it by 7, so I divide it by 10, and I'll get 7, because 77, because 77 divided
by 10 is 7.7, and the integer part is 7, so I get 7.
If I do a modularize of 10, I'll actually again get 7, why will you get again 7?
Very obvious because the nearest number that is divisible by 10 to 7 is 0, thereby you
get a remainder of 7, so you get 7.
After that, if you again try to divide it by 10, this time you'll end up getting 0,
because if I take 7 divided by 10, it'll be 0.7, hence the integer part is 0, so can I
say if I get an integer part as 0, can I say I've extracted all the digits I have, and
if you see the extraction has been done in the reverse order, and all the digits have
been extracted, as simple as that, so this is how you can easily extract all the digits.
So if I try to write the pseudocode, how will the pseudocode look like?
Can I say, if I have the N, I can take it from the user, I can take the N from the user,
and imagine I'm asking you to print all the digits, extract all the digits like 9, 8,
7, 7, and you can print it, so how will you do it?
It's very simple.
I will be like, okay while, I know what is the last step, last step is, the extraction
goes on from N when it is 7789 to N till 0, so I'll be like, I'll go on till N is greater
than 0, which means till N doesn't becomes 0, right, and can I say, the extraction is
very simple, the first time N was 7789, if I had to do an extraction, it's very simple,
can I say the last digit is nothing but N modularized N, if I do an N modularized N,
I'll get the last digit 9, and in order to get the next digit, what I do is, I say N
is N by 10, and this is how I can do it, so what will happen, let's do a dry run, at first
imagine I give, the user gives N as 7789, so this says 7789 greater than 0, which is
true, so the last digit happens to be 7789 modularized N, hence the last digit is 9,
if you want to print this last digit, you can definitely put a print operation, in C++
it is C out, in Java it is system.out.println, so you can go ahead and print the 9, once
you have done this, can I say if you do 7789 by 10, then the N will reduce itself, what
will be the value of N now, can I say the value of N will be nothing but 778, this is
how the first iteration, first iteration will happen, and then it will reach here, then
again goes here, when it goes here, it will be a new iteration, and can I say this time
the iteration will be 778, because N has changed itself to 778, and 778 greater than 0, what
I'll do is, I'll quickly erase this, because it's the next iteration, so let's quickly
erase this, and the next iteration what will happen, it will say 778 modularized N, the
last digit this time will be 8, again you can print that last digit, and this time it
will be 778 by 10, hence N will become 77, again the iteration will go and will be 77
greater than 0, and this way all these steps will be performed at the end of the day, the
value of N, yes the value of the N will be 0, hence the while loop will be false, and
I can say that the execution has been completed, and you have successfully extracted all the
digits in the reverse fashion, very important in the reverse fashion, got it, this is what
is the concept of extraction of digits, and this is going to help you solve a lot of other
problems as well.
So now let's look at the first problem, it states count digits, let's understand the
problem, given the number N, find out and return the digits present in a number, very
simple, it says 156 is the number, and the number of digits is 3, imagine the N is given
as 7, it has just one digit, so it will be given an N, and it will tell me the number
of digits, so if I go back to my iPad, can I say, if I give you the number 7789, this
has 4 digits, can you solve this problem, using the extraction of digits, can you, you
will be like, this is super easy, why, because you know the extraction of digits, you know
one digit, two digit, three digit, four digit, the digits are extracted four times, so can
I say, I can give something like a counter variable over here, and you know the number
of times the extraction happens, that is the number of times the digit will be, so can
I say, I can put a counter equal to counter plus 1 on the logic of extraction of digits,
if I do this, can I say, I'll be able to count the number of digits, and eventually if I
print the count over here, can I say, that I'll always have the count of digits of any
given N I can. Usually in coding rounds or in your interviews, you just have to code
the function, the function is an int function, that means you have to return the count of
digits, and they'll be giving you the input, so you are given the variable, you just have
to return, you have to just write the code inside the function, int main and everything
will be written on the backend, I've already discussed about this in the pattern video,
in case you haven't watched it, please go back and watch it. So this was the code that
we discussed on the iPad, right, so the count stores the count of digits, so I'll just return
the count, and then I'll go ahead and run the code, and I'll see that it is running
absolutely fine, and then I'll go ahead and submit this. So this is how you can easily
solve this particular problem. Now remember one thing, this last digit does not have any
significance, so you can remove it. So that was for extraction of digits, but this is
kind of reducing the numbers, so the number of times it is divisible by 10 is the number
of times the digits are. Now since I've removed the modular operation, we observe something,
can I say the number of times it is getting divisible by 10, the number of times it is
getting divisible by 10 is the count of the digits, it is, and this is where something
like logarithmic, log base 10, 7789, if you do this in your calculator, you'll actually
get something like 3.89 something. So this is the value that you'll get if you do a log
base 10 of the number, and then if you can add a 1 to it, this will be 4.89, and if you
take an integer of it, that will be 4. This is another way to find count of digits. What
you do is very simple, you say count is equal to log 10, the number, plus 1, and you're
saying take the integer, or you can just autocast it, like typecast it to integer.
This is how, whatever you get, this is converted to an integer. If you're getting 4.89, it
will be truncated to 4. And now let's run this and see if it is running fine. Okay,
so it says out of scope, log 10 was not declared. So if you find such errors, what you can do
is you can go to hash include. That's basically because in their backend, they might not have
added all the directories. You can go ahead and add all the directories and that will
start working fine. Once you've done this, you can go and compile and you're seeing that
this is also running fine. This is one of the other ways to count digits as well. But
the primary concept is extraction of digits and that is what you should focus on. Now
if I discuss the time complexity over here, what will be the time complexity? The time
complexity will be nothing but log base 10 N. This is the big go of time complexity.
Why log base 10 N? The reason was very simple. You saw this is getting divisible by 10. How
many times is the loop running? The number of times it is getting divisible by 10. This
is why you will see time complexity is near about log base 10 N. This was 3.89 near about
4. The number of times this loop did run was 4. Yeah, you can avoid these operations. These
are single operations because imagine the number being very large. These will be considered
as unit operations. That is why the time complexity is log base 10 N. Got it? Whenever there is
division, remember this, whenever there is division, if the division is happening by
10, you say log base 10 N. If the division is happening by 2, you say log base 2 N. If
the division is happening by 5, you say log base 5 N. This is how you compute the time
complexity of like, this is how the logarithmic time complexities are. So whenever you're
writing a logic where the number of iterations depends on division and you're dividing, dividing,
that is when something like logarithmic will come into the time complexity. That time the
time complexity will not be VGO of N. If the number of iterations is based on division,
time complexity will be logarithmic. Remember this always. So you solved the first problem
count digits. The next problem is reverse a number. Let's go to the problem. It states
write a program to generate the reverse of a given number. Print the corresponding reverse
number. If a number has trailing zeros, then its reverse will not include them. For example,
the reverse of 100400 will be 401 instead of 00401 and these are some of the examples.
So let's get back to our extraction of digits concept. So according to the problem, what
they are wanting is, if I'm giving you the number 7789, the reverse of this number will
be 9877. Now we know that the extraction of digits happens in the reverse fashion where
we generate 9, then we generate 8, then we get 7, then we get 7. Somehow we need 9877
which is the similar fashion. This is where the basic maths comes in. What you do is,
you define a variable sum or maybe reverse number. Reverse number equal to zero. And
you say reverse number equal to reverse number into 10 plus last digit. Remember this. This
is what you say. Reverse number into 10 plus last digit. Let's see how it works. So I'm
saying initially reverse number is zero to start off. Let's do the step by step. First
step, 9 gets generated. So what am I doing is, zero into 10 because reverse number is
zero at the first step. At the first step, 7789, 10 will generate 9 and N would have
as of now become something like 7789 by 10. So N would have as of now become 778 and reverse
number says, reverse number is zero into 10 plus the last digit 9. So the number becomes
or rather the reverse number as of now is 9. Right? This is what the first iteration
is. Let's do the next iteration. The next iteration will be, I'll just quickly omit
this off. So the next iteration, can I say it's 778 greater than zero and 778 modulo
10. Hence the last digit is 8. I can't say this. And this will be 778 by 10. So N will
become 77. This time, reverse number is stored as 9 because you stored reverse number as
this value. So this is 9. So what do you do is, you say 9 into 10 plus the last digit
8. What do you get is, 9 into 10 plus the last digit 8 which makes it 98. The next time
you get 7, the reverse is 98 into 10 plus 7 which is 987. Next time it is 7. So 987
into 10 plus 7 is 9877. So you got the reverse number there. Why it's simple? Why did this
work? It's very easy. Understand, you're getting in last digit, you're easily getting
the last digit, 9. And after that you're getting the next last digit 8 and you somehow want
to add 8 to that 9. You somehow want to add 8 to that 9. And the easiest way is, if you
can somehow add a zero to this 9, it will become 90. And then if you add 8 to it, it
will become 98. Similarly, if you want to add 7 to it, if you want to add a 7 to it,
make it 987. You again add a zero and then a 7 to it, it becomes 987. Again, if you want
to add a 7, you again add a zero. This is why at every step, I am doing reverse number
into 10. Whatever you have generated into 10, that will allow the last unit digit to
be zero. Then when you add a digit, it goes and gets into that place. As simple as that.
So again, you saw that extraction of digits is actually handy. So what I'll do is I'll
take the number and I'll keep the reverse num equal to zero. And then I'll go ahead
and say n greater than zero. And I can say last digit is n modulo 10. I can say reverse
number is reverse number into 10 plus last digit. And I can say n is n by 10. And the
same time I can say cout of reverse number is what I need. Perfect. And I'll quickly
run the code and see if it is running fine. It is. Let's quickly sum up this and this
should be running fine. This dead. So the reverse number is solved again with the concept
of extraction of digits. Next problem is check palindrome. Now when I go to the palindrome
problem, let's understand the problem. It states write a program to determine if a given
number is palindrome or not. Print true if it is palindrome or false otherwise. So over
here it states palindrome are the numbers for which reverse is exactly same as the original
one. For example one to one. Because if you take one to one and you do a reverse of it,
one to one's reverse is one to one. That is why it is called as palindrome. So if I go
to the iPad and I write some other palindrome numbers, it's like one double three one. If
you write the reverse of it, it stays still one double three one. Something like 11. 11
in itself is a palindrome. Seven. Seven in itself is a palindrome. Whereas one to three,
the reverse of one to three is three to one. This is not a palindrome. So any number which
on reversal is the same number is a palindrome number. So the definition of palindrome number
says reverse of a number. So if I somehow can generate the reverse of a number, if I somehow
can generate the reverse of a number, which I've already did and then compare it with the original
N and if they come out to be same, can I say they are palindrome? I can. So over here, if you
remember, we took a reverse number and at the end of the day, the reverse number was nothing but the
reverse number. And now if I can compare this reverse number with the original number, with the
original number, which is N and if they come out to be same, I can say it is palindrome. Like if
this is true, I can say it is palindrome or I can say it is not palindrome. Can I say it? But wait,
if you remember, we were dividing N by 10 and at the end of the day, N was zero. So does N have
the original number? No, because we are doing operations with N, which has made N to be zero
at the end of the day. So what I need to do is maybe I need to store a duplicate of N in some
top variable and instead of comparing it with N, I can compare it with a duplicate because N will
be zero at the end of the extraction of digits. It's very important to store a copy of N somewhere
so that it can be used to compare it with the reverse of a number. That is the only change
that you have to do and that is the only thing that you have to keep in mind. So if you remember,
this was the code. So what I'll do is I'll just go ahead and say duplicate equal to N
and over here I say if do is equal to equal to reverse number, I can go ahead and print true,
which is what they want, which is true or else you can just go ahead and print false.
That is what they required. I'll quickly run it and see if it is running fine. It should be and
let's quickly submit this. On submitting you see that it is running absolutely fine. The next one
is GCD or HCF but before that we will be solving Armstrong numbers. So what is the definition of
Armstrong number? It's very simple. Imagine you're given this number 371. You take three cube,
seven cube plus one cube. If taking the cubes of these numbers like cubes of these digits
and adding them up sums up to the number itself, that is what you call as an Armstrong number.
Even if you take 1634, one cube plus six cube plus three cube plus four cube, if you sum them up,
you actually get 1634. But something like 35, if you take three cube plus five cube, this is not
going to be equal to 35. This is going to be equal to 134. So this and this are not same. Whereas 1634
and the summation of cubes of its digits is 1634. So you call 1634 as an Armstrong number
or 371 as an Armstrong number. So I hope you've got the definition of Armstrong number.
If you have got the definition of Armstrong number, you know how to solve it. I've already
taught you the extraction of digits. You know how do you extract nine? You know how do you extract
eight? You know how do you extract seven? You just have to do a cube of it. So can I see this time
instead of taking any such duplicate or reverse n, I can just take a summation because I need to
sum cubes and last digit is what I have to sum. Can I say sum equal to sum plus last digit multiplied
thrice, last digit into last digit into last digit. Can I do this? So first time nine comes in,
what happens? Nine into nine into nine gets added to sum. Next time eight comes in,
eight into eight into eight gets added to the sum. So everything is getting added.
First time, nine into nine, sorry, nine into nine into nine got, next time eight went eight
into eight into eight. Next time, seven came in seven into seven into seven. Next time again,
seven came in seven into seven into seven. So can I say at the end of the day,
Some will be storing the summation of digit cubes and after that you need to
just compare it with the original end. So maybe again keep a duplicate variable
which stores the end because at the end of the day you have to compare if this
and the duplicate are same. If this is, then you say it is announced. If this is not,
it's not announced. Again what logic worked? Extraction of digits. If you know
how to extract digits, you can play around with them and you can solve this
problem. So Armstrong number is completed and the next problem that we will be
doing is print all divisors. So when I say print all divisors, what does it mean?
Imagine I take a number like 36 and ask you what are all the numbers that divide
36. So you can say 1 is something which completely divides 36. You can say 2 is
something which completely divides 36. You can again say 3 is something which
completely divides 36. 4 is something which completely divides. Is 5 something
which completely divides 36? No. If 36 is divided by 5, it leaves a remainder of 1.
So not 5. 6 is something which does it. 9 is something which does it. And 12 is
something which does it. And 18 is something which does it. And then 36 is
something which does it. If I talk about 36, the divisors of 36 are 1, 2, 3,
4, 6, 9, 12, 18 and 36. These are the divisors of 36. The question is very
straightforward. You have to print all of them in this particular order. Okay. Now
how do I do it? It's very simple. One thing I know for sure is if I'm talking about
divisors or factors, they're definitely going to lie between 1 to the number
itself. Can I say all the divisors will be between 1 to n itself because
anything greater than n will never divide n for sure? So if I know all the
divisors are going to be between 1 and n, can I just loop from 1 to n? That's my
first thought process. Since I know the divisors are from 1 to n, my first
thought process is very simple. Then let's do one. Let's start the loop from i
equal to 1, i lesser than equal to n and i plus plus. This is something I know
for sure. So i is used to loop around. Now the first value of i is 1, then it's 2,
then it's 3, then it's 4, then it's 5 and then so on till 36 in this case if it is
n. So how do you determine that this i is a part of all the divisors? It's very
Can I say if it is completely dividing, if i is completely dividing n, then it is a
factor or a divisor. And what do you mean by completely dividing? It should leave a
remainder of 0. When I say leaving a remainder of 0, does it mean if I do a
modulated of i, if I do n module i, the value should be 0 because it's
completely divisible. But what I will do is I'll say okay if n module i is equal
to equal to 0, I will go ahead and print i in C++, C out in Java system dot out dot
print out. I'll go ahead and print out i. In this way I'll be able to print all the
factors of a particular n. If I talk about the time complexity, ask you what
is the time complexity of this code? You'll be like Stryver, it's very simple.
Since the loop is running from 1 to n, it's taking n iterations. And this is an
unit operation so let's not calculate it. Thereby the time
complexity of this particular approach is nothing but BGO of n. Very simple.
Over here they've given us everything. They want us to write this print divisors
function. Let's write the print divisors function. It takes an n and as I said
it's very simple. You go from 1, you go on till n, let me say i, this one. And you
know if n module i is equal to equal to 0, you say C out i and then you give a
bit of space. That's what you need to write.
And on submitting you will see that this is running absolutely fine. But the time
complexity is BGO of n. I don't want a BGO of n time complexity. Can I do it in
a much better way? I can't. But it requires a bit of mathematical observation.
Let's see that mathematical observation. So for 36 I said that 1 was a factor. If
1 is a factor, 1 has to be multiplied with something in order to get 36. So 1
was multiplied with 36. And if you carefully observe, if this is 1 and the
number is 36, the other number will always be n by 1. Very simple. If it is 2, the other
number will be n by 2 which is 36 by 2. That means 18. So you get 18. Next time it
was 3. So the next time it is 3. So when I take 3, it is nothing but 12, 36 by 3.
Because 3 into 12 will be 36. The next time when I take 4, it is 4 into 9. The next time
when I take 6, it is 6 into 6. Next time, the next factor is actually 9. And then
you multiply it with 4. The next factor is 12 and you multiply it with 3. And the
next factor is 18. You multiply it with 2. And the next time it is 36, you multiply
it with 1. So if I have to write all the factors, these are all the
factors. Right? But do you have a bit of observation? If I draw a line at this
portion, if I draw a line at this portion, and I take this and I take this, aren't they
equal? 1 into 36, 36 into 1. So can I say, even if I consider everything before the
orange line, I will get 1, I'll get 2, I'll get 3, I'll get 4, I'll get 6, I'll get 9,
I'll get 12, I'll get 18, and I'll get 36. Even if I take everything before the orange
line, even if I take everything before this orange line, do I get all the facts? I do.
So do I need to go beyond this orange line? No. So what is this orange line? If you
carefully observe, what are you doing? A small number into a big number, a small
number into a big number, a small number into a big number, same number, same
number. And then a big into small, a big into small, a big into small. Can I say,
this is nothing but the square root of n, because when you take square root of n,
square root of 36 is 6. Beyond square root, the numbers will grow, the numbers
will grow, and it is nothing but a replication of the upper half, the
replication of the upper half. So thereby, this is nothing but a repetition of the
upper half. Thereby I can say, even if you loop till square root of n, even if you
loop till square root of n, you actually can get your factors. How? If this is 1,
this has to be n by 1. If this is 2, this has to be n by 2. If this is 3, this has
to be n by 3. If this is 4, this has to be n by 4. If this is 6, this has to be n
by 6. So can I say, now the looping is going to be very straightforward. I loop
from i equal to 1 till i less than equal to square root of n and i plus plus. Can I do that?
And can I say, if n modulo i is a factor, then print i as one of the factors,
print i as one of the factors. What is the other factor? We just now found out
the other factor was n by i. But we need to be careful. What is the careful
observation? If it is 6, the other factor might be 6. They are not two different
factors. So if you're taking the second factor, if you're taking the second
factor to n by i, just make sure that n by i is not equal to i. Because the
second factor might turn out to be the same factor. It's very important. The n by
i, which is the second factor, must be compared with i. And if they're not same,
you can say that, maybe print, that's your another factor. That's it. So first, check
if i is a factor, print it. Now the other factor, n by i, with which the i will be
multiplied, just check if this is not equal to i. If it is not, that's the
second factor. That's it. So if you go ahead and print this, the printing will
be something like this. First 1 and 36 will get printed. Next 2 and 18 will get
printed. Next 3 and 12 will get printed. Next 4 and 9 will get printed. Next one i is 6.
6 gets printed, but the other factor is 6. And it fails this condition check.
Thereby, the other 6 doesn't get printed. So all the factors are printed, but
they're not printed in a proper, yes, they're not printed in a sorted way. So
what you can do is, whenever you are getting all the factors, probably you can
store them into a data structure. And if you have seen the C++ STL video, you know
which data structure you can use. You do not know what will be the size or what
will be the number of factors. The data structure that you will be using is a
list, a list in Java or a vector in C++. You'll be using an undefined, like you
cannot define the size of the data structure. We'll be using a list, okay. And
in that list, you can store it, you can store it, store, store, store. So
everything will be stored in the list. Once you have stored in the list, sort
the list. And if you sort the list, you will get everything in the sorted
fashion. So if I go back to the code, what did I say? We will be going till
square root of n, right. We will be going till square root of n. We know this is a factor.
And we need a list now. So let's take a list. This is our list, vector. And we
know ls.push back of i, we push back i. And we know the other factor is
n by i. If this is not equal to i, that's the other factor. Again, we will say list
Can you store the other factor? The other factor is n by i. Once you have stored
everything, can you go ahead and say over here, sort ls.begin, ls.end. Once you
have done this, just need to print it. You know how to print it. This is how you
print the list. C++ STL video guys. So I'll just iterate on the list and I'll
print the list with space. So all of them are correct. I'll go ahead and print and
it will be correct. Why did I sort it? Because they wanted us to print
everything in the sorted order. It's very important to sort the list. If I talk
about the time complexity, what will be the time complexity? Something before
discussing the time complexity, you're writing i less than equal to square root
of n. Instead of this, because square root is a function, and every time the
function will be called, because square root is a mathematical function in C++
STL. This will be called every time, which will take time itself. Instead of
writing this, you can actually write i into i lesser than equal to n. It will be
like when i reaches 6, it will be like 6 into 6 lesser than equal to 36. It will
work. But normally it goes to 7. 7 into 7 is not equal to 36. So this will be false.
Alright. So this is the other way of writing for the square root. This is
what you can write. So can I say this loop is running for, we go off square
root of n times. Can I say this? That this loop is running for, we go off square
root of n times. And then the number of factors, whatever is the number of factors,
you're sorting it. The internal sorting function takes n log n. What is the
internal sorting function taking? n log n. What is n? n is the number of
factors. n is the number of factors. Right? So can I say n is the number of
factors. n is not the original n. It is the number of factors. And then you're
going ahead and printing it. So again, taking a number of factors time to print
it, whatever is the number of times. So the overall time complexity in this case
is we go off square root of plus we go off number of factors into log of number
of factors. So number of factors into log of, if I write it properly, number of
factors. Got it? And then plus this. So we go off this plus we go off this plus we go
off this is the time complexity. But the motive was to teach you that you can
also find factors in we go off square root of n. Got it? I can say I've also
done print all divisors in both the ways. Now what is the next question? It
states check for prime. So what is the definition of a prime number? A lot of
you will say a number that is divisible by one and itself. This is a wrong
definition. Why? Because according to this definition, one is a prime number.
Because one is divisible by one and one is divisible by itself, which is one.
It's a wrong definition. Instead of this, the definition that you should always
keep in mind is a number that has exactly two factors, one and itself.
That's a better definition. One and itself. A number that has two factors, which is
one and itself. So if you remember, we just now computed factors. So if you're
given a number, something like 11. Can I say 11 has a factor of 1 and 11 itself?
Any other number doesn't divide. So 11 is a prime number. If I say 13, 13 is a
prime number because 1 and 13 divides it. If I say 5, 5 is a prime number because 1 and 5
divides it. If I say 4, 4 is not a prime number. Why? Because it is divisible by 1.
It is divisible by 2. It is also divisible by 4. So there are three
factors. So 4 is not a prime number. If I take 8, it is not a prime number. Why?
Divisible by 1, 2, 4, 8 is not a prime number. Something like 17 is a prime number
because divisible by 1 and 17. So what is the first? The brute force. What is the
definition of brute force? The algorithm which is the first algorithm or the
initial algorithm that comes to your mind. Okay. So can I say the simplest way
to check is I will do one thing. I'll keep a counter equal to zero and I know
it exactly has two factors. So run a loop from 1 and I'll go on till n and I'll
say I plus plus and I'll say hey listen if it is a factor it will be completely
divisible by I. Hence it will leave a remainder zero and I'll do a counter
plus plus and can I say at the end of the day if the counter turns out to be
two then I'll say it's a prime number or else it's not a prime number. So can I
say this is the extreme brute force approach and if I write the extreme
brute force approach what will be the time complexity of the extreme brute
force approach? Can I say I'm running a loop n and these are unit operations so
I can ignore. So can I say the time complexity will be b go of n because I'm
running a loop to check for every I which can be a factor and then I'm
checking it and there is and after that there are conditional checks which are
unit operations can be avoided. So this is b go of n and we know that factors
are involved. In the previous problem we did learn that all the factors can be
found in square root of n. Why? Because if you remember 36, 36 had a factor one
and the corresponding factor like the corresponding other factor was 36. 2's
18, 3's 12, 4's 9 and 6 6. Even if you checked till square root of n you could
actually count all the factors and all the factors were 1 2 3 4 6 9 12 18 36 you
can count all the factors. Even if you loop till square root of n. So why are you
looping till b go of n? Kindly loop till square root of n. So what you'll do is
you'll say I equal to 1 I into I lesser than n I've already taught you this and
counter equal to 0 and you'll say if n modulo I is equal to equal to 0 that is
definitely a factor and at the same time the other factor has to be different and
if the other factor is different then it will also be counted and then you can
have a same check if counter is equal to equal to 2 prime else not a prime number
as simple as that and if I talk about the time complexity this loop ends up
running for b go of square root of n if someone is coming up and asking you how
do you check for a prime number you say I know the square root method because I
know the observation for every factor there is the other corresponding number
with which it has to get multiplied in order to get the number thereby I can
just go up to square root of n nothing beyond it because till square root of n
I'll get all the factors. So this is the code that I did right in the iPad so
I'll now quickly go ahead and submit this and see if it is working fine. It is indeed
working fine. So we have completed the check for prime. So apparently you have
completed everything and the GCD or the HCF is left. So let's go across and learn
the GCD or HCF and then come back and take it over. So what do you mean by GCD
or HCF? It's very simple. Greatest common divisor or highest common factor. Let me
give you an example. If I give you two numbers n1 equal to 9 and n2 equal to 12
you need to find the highest common factor or greatest common divisor that
actually divides n and that divides 9 and 12. So if I write down all the factors
of 9 it is 1, 3 and 9. If I write down all the factors of 12 it is 1, 2, 6 and 12.
Even 3, 4. These are all the factors of 12. So if I ask you the common factors, the
common factors if I go ahead and mark it is 1, 1, it is 3, 3. So there are two common
factors. Out of these two common factors which is the highest one 3. So I can say
the GCD of 9, 12 is 3 because 3 is the largest number that divides 9 and 12
both. If I ask you the GCD of 11 and 13 what will it be? It will be 1. Because if
you try to write down all the factors of 11 it's going to be 1 and 11. All the
factors of 13, 1 and 13. So the common one is just 1 and that is the GCD. So there
will always be a GCD because 1 is a number that divides every other number.
So for every given two numbers there will always be a GCD or HCF. If I ask you
what is the GCD of 20, 30 or rather 20, 40. What is the GCD of 20, 40?
Because for 20, 20 is a factor and for 40, 20 is also a factor. So that's why 20. So
for two given numbers one of them can also be a GCD of those two given numbers.
So that is what is the definition of GCD.
So all of you know, so you know how to find factors of two given numbers. A given
N1 and a given N2. So in the last two problems you have learned how to find
factors. So imagine it's like N1 is 9 and N2 is 12. So can I say if I loop from
1 to 12 and for every number I'll check if they're dividing both. Does 1 divide
both? Yes. 1 as of now is the largest factor. Does 2 divide both? No. Does 3 divide
both? Yes. So 3 is the largest factor. If I can check every number and if every
number divides both of them, if a number divides both of them I just replace that
with my GCD's answer. The largest number that I get that divides both of them
will be my GCD. If I try to write it, can I write this as i equal to 1? Maybe I
will loop till N1. Maybe. I plus plus and I'll see if N1 modulo i equal to
equal to 0 and then N2 modulo i equal to equal to 0. As of now I know one
thing for sure. Any given two numbers, any given two numbers will always have a
GCD of 1. So GCD will be replaced by i. Can I say this? Because i is starting
from 1, so it goes from 1, then it goes to 2, then goes to 3. So whichever
number divides both of them it just keeps on getting replaced. The last
number which will be stored in GCD will definitely be the largest because i is
moving in the increasing fashion. Very simple. Now you might ask me, but Stryver,
what if N was given as 12 and N2 was given as 9? Then the for loop would have
been running for 12 times. But I know one thing for sure that if i is 10, that 10
will not divide 9. There is no point in checking. So can I say instead of running
till N1, I can actually run it for something like minimum of N1, N2
because I know if I run till minimum of N1, N2 like 9, if I run till 9 that
will suffice. Running 10, 11 doesn't make sense. For example if the number was 20
and 40, if I run till 20 that will work because 20 is the largest factor I can
have. Running it for 21, 22 will not make sense. So can I say I can run the loop
till minimum of N1 command? I can. Thereby, can I say the time complexity will be
we go of minimum of N1, N2 whichever is minimum till that I'll run the loop so
thereby the time complexity is minimum of N1, N2. Now you might have
questions in your head. But Stryver, we are trying to find IS and over
here what are you doing? You're going from 1, 2, 3, 4 and you're checking everyone. But
what if N1 is 20, N2 is 40 and I do the other way. Yes, I do the other way and I
say I'll run it from minimum of N1, N2, I greater than equal to 1, I minus
and I'll say if N1 modulo I equal to equal to 0 and and N2 modulo I equal to
equal to 0, I will print that as my GCD and I'll break and I'll break and you
know what is the task of break? It always breaks out from the outer loop. Not this
is a conditional statement. This is not a loop. For this break which is the loop
that is outside this break, this one. It will break out from this. How does it work?
The minimum of 20, 40 is 20. So 20. 20 modulo 20 equal to equal to 0. Yes. 40
modulo 20 equal to equal to 0. Yes. Print GCD as 20. Yes. Break. So the program
terminates. In this way you will say, in this way it will have a better complexity
because the moment you are getting someone from behind, it breaks out. You
might give me this. Yeah, definitely this might turn out to be a better one for a
lot of cases but still the worst case will be minimum of N1, N2.
Imagine I give you two numbers. N1 equal to 11, N2 equal to 13. In this case what
will happen? For 11 and 13, the highest common factor is 1. It will start from
11, 10, 9 but will not find anyone till 1. It will eventually loop from 11 to 1.
So no matter what you do, the time complexity will be still this because if
both the numbers have GCD as 1, it ends up running completely. The loop ends up
running completely and you know when you determine the time complexity, taught you
in the time complexity lecture, you always take worst case. You always take
worst case. The worst case is when you run it till 1. We saw the previous
method was a brute force method and was taking linear time complexity. Now there
is an algorithm known as eucalydian algorithm which is going to take much
much lesser time. So let's learn about it. So what is eucalydian algorithm? It
states if we're given two numbers N1, N2, the GCD of N1, N2, whatever is
the GCD of N1, N2, that's equivalent to the GCD of N1 minus N2, N2, where N1
is greater than N2. Usually in books you'll find them written as GCD of A, B
is equal to GCD of A minus B, B where A is greater than B. This is what the
eucalydian algorithm states. If you want a mathematical proof of it, you can
definitely Google search. There's a huge mathematical proof to it. Again we will
not go deep into the mathematical proof because it is not required in
programming world. You just need this concept. So just have the concept. Now if
I try to prove this with induction it's very simple. If I give you two numbers
imagine 15 and 20. So it basically states the greater number and the
smaller number. What is the GCD of 20, 15? We know the GCD of 20, 15 is 5.
So it states the GCD of 20, 15, the greater number 20 and the smaller
number 15 is equal to, it states greater minus smaller, 20 minus 15, 5, the
smaller number 15. So what is the GCD of 5, 15? That is also 5. So again by
induction also you can prove it. You can take any two numbers and you'll be able
to prove that they are same. So I can say that the GCD of 20, 15 is
equivalent to the GCD of 5, 15. Now you apply the eucalydian on the first two
numbers and whatever you get that will always be a truncated number. You saw 20
getting truncated to 5. Again you will apply eucalydian to this. If you try to apply
eucalydian to 5, 15 it has to be the greater number at first. So apparently
you have to apply eucalydian to 15, 5 because 15 is the greater number.
Right? So what do you do is you say okay let's apply eucalydian to 15, 5.
It will be like GCD of 15 minus 5, 10, 5. Again you can apply eucalydian to 10, 5.
If you apply eucalydian to 10, 5 it will be greater is 10, 10 minus 5 is 5, 5, 5.
Again if you apply eucalydian to 5, 5 it'll be, both of them are same,
any one can be at the front, 0, 5. So 1 apparently becomes 0. The moment
one of the numbers becomes 0, the other number is actually a GCD, is actually a
GCD. So the GCD of 20, 15 is this. What do you do is you take two numbers, apply
eucalydian, get it smaller, apply eucalydian, get it smaller, get it smaller, get it
smaller till one of them is 0. If one of them is 0, the other is 0. So the
algorithm is quite simple. Start with a, b, keep on truncating, keep on
minus b, b and keep on doing till one of them, the greater number becomes 0.
As simple as that. But there's a catch. This might end up taking a lot more time.
Imagine I give you a number like a equal to 52 and b equal to 10. So it'll be like
what will you do? You will say GCD of 52, 10 truncated to GCD 42, 10.
Truncated to GCD 32, 10. Truncated to GCD 22, 10. Truncated to GCD 12, 10.
Truncated to GCD 2, 10. And then you again take the bigger number at first,
10, 2. And then you'll be again like truncated to 8, 2. Truncated to
6, 2. 4, 2. 2, 2 and 0, 2. And ultimately 2 is left because
everything comes up. So it's a lot of sticks. It's a lot of sticks. It might not improve the
linear complexity by so much. But there's a catch over here. If it is 52 and it was 10
and you're reducing it with 10 every time and you ended up at a place of 2, 10.
Isn't it equivalent to saying you're dividing it by 10? And you're like 52, if you
did it 5 times. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5. And you ended up having the remainder because you're
minus 10, minus 10, minus 10, minus 10 till it is possible. It's equivalent to saying you
subtract it till it was possible or till it is greater. Can I say, instead of
subtracting it 5 times, you could have directly gone from here to here by
saying 52 modulo 10, 10. That's same. 2, 10. That is same instead of
subtracting 10, 5, 10. Directly get 2, 10. Even from 10, 2 to 0, 2, you
could have directly gone by saying 10 modulo 2 because that is what you did
indirectly. Simple maths. So can I say the algorithm in a better sense will be GCD
of A, B, where definitely A is greater than B, is equal to A modulo B, B.
That's a better word. And you go on doing till it becomes 0. As simple as that. You always take the
greater number. So the logic is very simple. Forget about A and B. The logic is very
simple. The greater modulo is smaller. That's the logic. And you go on till one of them
is 0. And if one of them is 0, remember this, if one of them is 0, the other is GCD, the
other is GCD. As simple as that. If I try to quote this up, try to quote this up, you're given A, you're given B. Can I say you go on till both of them are greater
greater than 0. Basically. And I know one of them will be greater. Either A will be greater. In that
case, I'll do A modulo B. Or else if B is greater, I'll do B modulo A. Instead of swapping, changing, because I did not want to get into swapping, changing. Why?
Over here it was 2, 10. So A was this, B was this. And you swapped it to this. I did not want to implement that. I just, I knew now 10 will be modulated. So what I did was I implemented it in such a way
stating, if A is greater, A will be modulated. If B is greater, B will be modulated. And once this is over, if A is 0, if A becomes 0, the while loop is false. Can I say the GCD will be B? I will. Or else can I say the GCD will be print of A? Simple.
Yes. You can, you can just take this example, 52, 10, and you can do a dry run on this. And you will see that eventually one of them will become 0. And that is when the looping ends.
And the time complexity of this equilaudian algorithm is we go of log of phi minimum of A, B. While log, if you remember, I clearly stated during the digit extraction, or in the pattern videos, or the time complexity videos, that whenever there is division happening, whenever there is division happening, the number of iterations will be in terms of logarithm.
Over here there is modulo. You are reducing the number by division. The modulation operations are happening. Thereby the time complexity will be in terms of logarithm. Now, Wi-Fi, why not something like log base 10? In the digit extraction, it is always n by 10. Over here, this A and B, it's always changing, fluctuating. You're not sure what will be A and B. Depending on different examples, it will fluctuate.
That is why they're giving it a term phi. If you want to know what is phi in depth, there's a huge mathematical proof to it. Not required. You can read it, but it's not required. And minimum of A, B. Because that is the initial number where you start from. That's the initial number where you start to do it. So that's why the time complexity is this. No one is going to ask you how and everything. Just keep it in mind that the time complexity is log phi minimum of A, B.
This is the equivalent.
I've written the same code after if I'm not given else because if this line executes, the function would have end and this line will not execute. That's why. So now I'll go ahead and run this code and it is running absolutely fine. And if I'll submit this, we get the correct answer.
So with this, we'll be wrapping up the basic maths. Next is basic recursion. I've already made videos on it. I'll be attaching them to the playlist. So watch this maths video.
Who's that going towards the basic recursion video. Once you have done this, then we will be going across to the next topic. That is basic hashing and I'll be explaining hashing in depth.
But I hope for this video, you've understood basic maths completely just in case you have. Please hit that like button and to follow our ritual, do comment understood so that I get an idea that you guys are understanding and you have watched the video.
Till here, if you're new to our channel, what are you? Please, please do consider subscribing to us because that is the only thing that keeps me motivated to make these kind of content. And here with this, I'll be wrapping up this video. Let's be in some other video till then goodbye.
Don't ever forget your gold.