She's got a smile, but it seems the mirror reminds me of childhood memories
Where everything wants to stretch as the bright blue skies
Now and then, when I see a face, she takes me away to that special place
And if I stand too long, I'd probably break down and cry
Oh, oh, oh, don't reach out tonight
It got eyes of the blue and skies that gave faith for the rain
I hated to look into those eyes and see it down to rain
Her hair reminds me of a long safe place where as a job I'd hang out
And bring all the thunder and the rain and the
Why did they pass me by giggling?
Oh, yeah
Oh, oh, oh oh
Sweet love of my eyes
Oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh
Oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, a, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, Oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh
That Gerrard.
Where do we go now?
B-i-i-i-i-i...
Ooh!
Whoa!
Where do we go?
Whoa, whoa, whoa, whoa!
Where do we go, you?
Winter, winter
All of my life